# Md. Sahidul Islam

House no. 169/A, Santiniketon, Niketon Bazar, Tejgaon Industrial Area, Dhaka-1208

□ (+88) 01737-272 633 | ☑ ripon.ru.statistics@gmail.com | ☑ ripon08054718 | 🛅 sahidul-islam-ripon-ab543342/

| ♥ ripon\_ru | ⑤ ripon.ru

"Be the change that you want to see in the world."



## **Summary** \_

MD. SAHIDUL ISLAM has been managing projects by analysing data and conducting research since 2012. With experience on various projects including Kala-azar disease prevention, Oral Cholera Vaccine programmes, maternal and child health, National Media Survey, Mobile Financial Services, local stability initiatives, good governance and capacity building programmes for various donors including USAID, DFID, InterMedia, CDC, Gallup, CIDA and various government and private funders. He designed, developed, implemented and managed or provided technical assistance to the management of the monitoring and evaluation of various projects in diverse conditions in internationally having worked in rural and remote area of Bangladesh.

Sahidul has developed, managed and implemented databases to track the flow of information within complex, multi-layered, geographically dispersed projects, placing a specific emphasis on data quality. He has vast experienced in Data analysis, project monitoring and evaluation and research with expertise knowledge in R Programming, SPSS, Stata, Matlab, Maple, Minitab with a solid background in statistics and having a strong technical aptitude.

## Work Experience \_

#### Vaccine & Logistic Management Assistant

WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION, BANGLADESH

Dhaka, Bangladesh Feb. 2019 -cont.

- · Collate and analyze data related to vaccines and logistics to strengthen routine and supplementary immunization services
- · Inventory/stock management with proper record keeping including planning, indenting and distribution of vaccine and logistics by way of coordinating with procurement and supply division, EPI, DGHS;
- · Management of vaccines, syringes, injection safety materials and other relevant logistics at the national level, including estimation of requirements, preparing indents, preparing schedules of deliveries and ensuring timely supply
- Undertake field visits to support quality distribution of vaccines and logistics and conduct 'on the job' trainings;
- Minimizing vaccine and injection stock-outs and reducing wastages;
- · Assist for evaluating vaccine and logistics requirement for supplementary immunization activities and any new vaccines introduction;

Statistical Officer Dhaka, Banaladesh

INTERNATIONAL CENTRE FOR DIARRHOEAL DISEASE RESEARCH, BANGLADESH (ICDDR,B)

Aug. 2018 - Oct. 2018

- Designing ways of collecting survey data, writhing program for cleaning, preparing and analysing the data.
- Prepared statistical modeling and reporting and draw conclusion from the data.
- Interpreting statistical analysis for policy development, evaluation &monitoring, forecasting, national statistics and dealing with queries for a range of clients.
- Developing statistical tools for data preparation and analysis.
- Develop automated reporting system using R markdown

#### **Monitoirng and Evaluation Officer**

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2018

INTERNATIONAL CENTRE FOR DIARRHOEAL DISEASE RESEARCH, BANGLADESH (ICDDR,B)

- Developed Monitoring & Evaluation guideline according to project goal for National Kala-azar Elimination Programme (NKEP).
- Implement the project monitoring & evaluation strategy and recommendation any possible changes based on data analysis by collecting sample from field on a periodic basis.
- Present findings at quarterly board meeting, making recommendations for improvements and acting as an M&E consultant to executives.
- Statistical modeling, data analysis and reports making in a monthly, quarterly, half yearly, and present the findings in board meeting.
- · Review the performance indicators and reports to the different stakeholders to suggest necessary changes and current status for program
- Provide statistical support example, sample size calculation, sampling techniques, statistical modeling, data analysis to other projects.

Research Manager Dhaka, Bangaldesh

KANTAR MRB Aug. 2014 - Apr. 2016

 Research and transform information from raw data into an easily understood analysis that identifies pattern, trend and insights for the program.

- Proposal writing & submission, questionnaire development, research designing, sampling preparation, statistical modeling and data analysis.
- Ensured accurate and consistent statistical analysis by meticulously going through the data validating results.
- Preparing presentation and delivering the projects output to clients.

**Analytics Executive**Dhaka, Bangladesh

KANTAR MRB

Seo. 2014 - Dec. 2016

- Successfully completed more than 20 projects including National Mobile Financial Service Survey (NMFSS), National Media Survey (NMS)
   etc
- Database preparation, data cleaning, error program writing and checking inconsistent data.
- Convert data into actionable insights by predicting and modeling future outcomes.
- CAPI (Computer Assist Personal Interview) and CATI (Computer Assist Telephonic Interview) and mobile base questionnaire development.
- Designed and built statistical analysis models on large datasets.
- Create visually impactful dashboards in Excel and Tableau for data reporting by using pivot tables and VLOOKUP. Extracted, interpreted and analyzed data to identify key metrics and transform raw data into meaningful, actionable information.

## **Education**

M.Sc. in Statistics Rajshahi, Bangladesh

DEPARTMENT OF STATISTICS, UNIVERSITY OF RAJSHAHI

Sep. 2012 - Mar. 2014

- CGPA: 3.778 (out of 4.0)
- Master Thesis: A Comparative Study between Independent Component Analysis (ICA) and Principal Component Analysis (PCA)

B.Sc. in Statistics Rajshahi, Bangladesh

DEPARTMENT OF STATISTICS, UNIVERSITY OF RAJSHAHI

Jan. 2017 - Sep. 2012

- CGPA: 3.42 (out of 4.0)
- - Undergraduate Project: Use of Paper on Academic Results: a case study on the students of Rajshahi University

### Skills

- Comprehensive advance knowledge of R Programming, IBM SPSS, Stata, MS Word, Excel, PowerPoint.
- Ability to work well with numbers and analyze complex data.
- Following 'best practice' in research design and documentation.
- In-depth knowledge of research tools and databases.
- Ability to work in a structured and organised manner.
- Experience of quantitative and qualitative research.
- Confidently communicate market research insights to influence business decisions.
- Expert-level understanding of performance evaluation, including the assessment of metrics, comparative analysis, and future projections based off of improvement.
- Familiar with data mining applications used to retrieve information for analysis, as well as electronic reporting tools.
- Excellent oral and written communication skills, evidenced by comfort in sharing and interpreting report data with managers and preparing statements to be reviewed by stakeholders.
- · Organized and detailed in all aspects of work.

## **Publications**.

- [1] Chowdhury R, Chowdhury V, Faria S, Islam S, Maheswary NP, Akhter S, Islam MS, Dash AP, Kroeger A, Banu Q. *Indoor residual spraying for kala-azar vector control in Bangladesh: A continuing challenge.* PLoS neglected tropical diseases. 2018 Oct 1;12(10):e0006846.
- [2] Islam MS, Hoque MA, Islam MS, Ali M, Hossen B, Binyamin M, Merican AF, Akazawa , Kumar N, Sugimoto M. "Mining Gene Expression Profile with Missing Values: An integrated implementation of Kernel PCA and Singular Value Decomposition". Current Bioinformatics, 13(2018):1-12, issn 1574-8936/2212-392X, doi 10.2174/157489361366618041315165413(2)
- [3] Hahn T, Rahman HU, Segall R, Heim C, Brunson R, Sharma A, Aslam M, Lara-Rodriguez A, **Islam MS**, Gupta N, Embry CS. "Remote access programs to better integrate individuals with disabilities." In Proceedings of the 18th International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on

- Computers and Accessibility 2016 Oct 23 (pp. 245-250). ACM.
- [4] Islam MS, Islam MS, Nasser M. "Principal Component Analysis versus Independent Component Analysis in Visualization of Clusters."
  In International Conference on Statistical Data Mining for Bioinformatics Health Agriculture and Environment 2012 Sep 30 (pp. 21-24).
- [5] Rajib Chowdhury, Vashkar Chowdhury, Sahidul Islam, Shyla Faria, Saiful Islam, Narayan Prosad Maheswary, Shireen Akhter, Aditya Prasad Dash, Axel Kroeger, Qamar Banu "Water Depth and Color Choice in Chikungunya Vectors in Bangladesh". World Health Organization, Dengue Bulletin
- [6] Md. Sahidul Islam, Md. Saimul Islam, Thomas Hahn "Prevalence & Factor Associated with Stunting and Severe Stunting among under Fives in Bangladesh: evidence from 2014 Bangladesh Demographic and Health Survey". (Submitted to Plos One)
- [7] Rajib Chowdhury, Vashkar Chowdhury, **Sahidul Islam**, Shyla Faria, Saiful Islam, Narayan Prosad Maheswary, Shireen Akhter, Aditya Prasad Dash, Axel Kroeger, Qamar Banu. **"Knowledge, Attitude and Practice related to Visceral Leishmaniasis"**. [Submitted to *Plos NTD*]

# **Conference Talks** [Selected]

- [1] Mohammad Wahiduzzaman, Sharmin Hossain, Md. Sahidul Islam, Andres Lechner, Liaquat Ali. "Clinical Outcome and Its Association with Adherence to Medical Advice among T2DM Subject Attending OPD: Experience from a Tertiary Care Hospital of Bangladesh" 8th regional public health conference, Bangladesh University of Health Science, 29-30 December 2017
- [2] Md. Sahidul Islam, Md. Saimul Islam, Thomas Hahn, and Mohammed Nasser. "Breast Cancer DNA Microarray Gene Expression Data Analysis using ICA." The 2nd International Conference on Statistics for Population and Development, organized by Dhaka University Statistics Department Alumni Association (DUSDAA), 27-29 December, 2015
- [3] Md. Sahidul Islam, Mohammed Ali, Md. Saimul Islam, Md. Binyamin, and Mohammed Nasser. "A Comparative Study between ICA, PCA and Their Robust Versions in Visualization of Clusters". An Proceedings of the International Conference on Applied Statistics in University of Dhaka, Bangladesh (ICAS'14), 27-29 December, 2014
- [4] Md. Bipul Hossen, Md. Binyamin, Md. Ali, Md. Saimul Islam, Md. Sahidul Islam, Md. Nasser, Md. Aminul Haque, Mashahiro Sugimoto. "Performance Evaluation of Several Hierarchical Clustering Algorithms with Proximity Measures". In Proceedings of the International Conference on "Statistics in planning and development: Bangladesh perspective", organized by Statistical Association Dhaka, Bangladesh)

## Honors & Awards

Oct. 2012 Placed **first position** in statsoft SATISTICA data analysis software competition organized by statsoft India, New Delhi facilitated by Department of Statistics, University of Rajshahi.

Mar. 2010 Selected for full free tution fee for placing 3rd within science faculty in first and second year bachelor exam.

Mar. 2014 Selected scholarship for getting outstanding academic results in masters exam.

## **Certifications**

## **Monitoring and Evaluation of Malaria Programs**

Measure Evaluation, USAID, CDC

M&E Fundamentals

16 Aug. 2017

GLOBAL HEALTH E-LEARNING CENTRE

USAID and Johns Hopkins University
20 Aug. 2017

#### **Global Disaster Risk Reduction and Management Pathway**

Humanitarian Learning Centre 28 Oct. 2018

R Programming Coursera

Johns Hopkins University, Bloomberg School of Public Health 01-30 Apr. 2014

Machine Learning Coursera

Stanford University 01 Apr.-31 May. 2014

The Data Scientist's Toolbox

Coursera

Johns Hopkins University, Bloomberg School of Public Health 01 May-31 May 2017

#### **Computing for Data Analysis**

JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, BLOOMBERG SCHOOL OF PUBLIC HEALTH

01 Nov.-3o Nov. 2013

Coursera

Regression Models Coursera

JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, BLOOMBERG SCHOOL OF PUBLIC HEALTH

01 Nov.-30 Nov. 2014

# **Programming & Computer Skills**

**Programming:** R Programming (advance), Python (moderate), Visual Basic (moderate), C# (basic), Java (basic), Matlab (moderate) **Data Analysis Software:** IBM SPSS (advance), Excel VBA (advance), Stata (advance), Statistica (basic), AMOS (moderate), Eviews (moderate),

Minitab (advance), Weka (advance), Tableau (basic)

Database: MS Access (advance), Epi-info (advance), FoxPro (advacne), SqLite (advance), MySql(moderate)

**Geo spatial/Mapping:** QGIS (moderate), R(advance), Python (moderate)

Presentation: MS Powerpoint(advance), Beamer (advance)

**Type-setting:** MS Word (advance), ETFX(advance)

# **Specialized trainings/ Workshops**

#### INTERNATIONAL

Training on CAPI Questionnaire Development and Data Preparation through Nfield

Park Street, Kolkata, India 02-08 May 2016

Organized by Kantar IMRB, Kolkata

Delhi, India

ORGANIZED BY KANTAR IMRB, DELHI, INDIA

01 Aug-30 Sep. 2016

**International Workshop on Large Scale National Survey** 

Training on IBM SPSS Data Collection and Survey Author

University of Rajshahi

Organized by Department of Statistics, University of Rajshahi, Supported by Higher Education Quality Enhancement Project (HEQEP)

18-19 Oct. 2012

**International Workshop on Health Statistics** 

Organized by Department of Statistics, University of Rajshahi, Supported by Higher Education Quality

**ENHANCEMENT PROJECT (HEQEP)** 

University of Rajshahi 20-22 Apr. 2012

#### **DOMESTIC**

**Workshop on Probability Theory and Application in Machine Learning** 

University of Rajshahi

Organized by Department of Statistics, University of Rajshahi, Supported by Higher Education Quality Enhancement Project (HEOEP)

09-10 Sep. 2011

**Workshop on Environmental Analysis under Climate Change** 

University of Rajshahi

Organized by Department of Statistics, University of Rajshahi, Supported by Higher Education Quality Enhancement Project (HEQEP)

27-27 Jul. 2012

## Workshop on Multivariate Calculus-1 for Machine Learning

University of Rajshahi

ORGANIZED BY DEPARTMENT OF STATISTICS, RAJSHAHI UNIVERSITY, SUPPORTED BY HIGHER EDUCATION QUALITY ENHANCEMENT PROJECT (HEQEP)

27-27 Jul. 2012

# References\_

Mr. Gunalan Karuppanan

Technical Officer, Immunization and Vaccine Development World Health Organization, Bangladesh

■ karuppanang@who.int

□ (+88) 017 13-205 865

Dr. Dinesh Mondal

Senior International Scientist

International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research Bangladesh (icddr,b)

✓ din63d@icddrb.org

**1** (+88) 017 12-027 091